Guide to the New-York Historical Society Building Renovations and Maintenance Records 1938-2017 NYHS-RG 4
New-York Historical Society
New-York Historical Society building renovations and maintenance records
1938-2017
New-York Historical Society
NYHS-RG 4
37.96 Linear feet in 27 document boxes, 2 flat boxes, and 5 drawers of oversize folders
The New-York Historical Society building renovations and maintenance records include files concerning the Central Park West physical plant from the late 1940s and forward. One major initiative that is especially well-documented in the record group is the extensive renovation work that began in planning about 1989 and concluded in 2000 with the opening of the Henry Luce III Center for the Study of American Culture. Various other large and small construction and maintenance projects are documented to some extent. The record group will continue to accrue new material over time.
Arrangement Note
The record group is organized such that projects with extensive records are described within their own series while projects documented in a more limited way are arranged together chronologically in a general series. The record group currently includes the following series:
Series I. General Subject Files
Series II. 1990s Capital Improvement Projects
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Materials are stored offsite and advance notice is required for use. Please contact manuscripts@nyhistory.org prior to your research visit to coordinate access. Keep in mind that it will take between two (2) and five (5) business days for collections to arrive, and you should plan your research accordingly.
Accruals Note
The record group is open for accruals of additional material.
Related Archival Materials Note
This finding aid relates to just one record group of the New-York Historical Society archives. For information about the other record groups and for overall information about the archives, please see the Guide to the New-York Historical Society Archives (NYHS-RG Archives). Other record groups that are processed and available to researchers and are especially related to the New-York Historical Society building renovations and maintenance records (NYHS-RG 4) are as follows:
The New-York Historical Society original buildings planning & construction records (NYHS-RG 3) include the files concerning buildings matters from the early 1940s and prior. Those records include the construction of N-YHS's building on 2nd Avenue (1850s), the central portion of the Central Park West building (1900s), and the expansion of Central Park West (1930s).
Scope and Contents Note
The New-York Historical Society building renovations and maintenance records include files concerning the Central Park West physical plant from the late 1940s and forward to the present. (For records related to the early 1940s and prior, including the construction of the Central Park West building, see the New-York Historical Society original buildings planning & construction records [NYHS-RG 3]). The record group was compiled from various sources and does not necessarily document, or document completely, all renovation work done over the decades.
One major initiative that is especially well-documented in the record group is the extensive renovation work that began about 1989 and concluded in 2000 with the opening of the Henry Luce III Center for the Study of American Culture (Luce Center). These records include planning documents, such as feasibility studies, proposals, and surveys, and implementation documents, such as contracts, change orders, construction meeting summaries, and payment requisitions. There is extensive correspondence with the architects, engineers, and city agencies that funded the project phases of the late 1990s. There are many architectural drawings, though these are related principally to the early planning work of 1989-1990 done by the firm of Allan Greenberg, Architect. In addition to the Luce Center, these records of projects from the 1990s include work related to the renovation of the Luman Reed Gallery, roof, façade, heating, ventilation, and air-conditioning (HVAC) systems, and other areas.
Aside from the capital improvement projects of the 1990s, several other projects, large and small, are documented to at least some extent, such as the initial installation of air-conditioning in the mid-1960s, the application to the Landmarks Preservation Commission to place a railing at the front entrance in the mid-1970s, and the development of the DiMenna Children's Museum in the late 2000s, as well as various unrealized proposals.
Architectural records.; Contracts.; Invoices.; Letters (correspondence); Photographs.; Requisitions.; Learned institutions and societies -- New York (State) -- New York -- Designs and plans.; Learned institutions and societies -- New York (State) -- New York -- Drawings.; Libraries and institutions -- New York (State) -- New York -- Designs and plans.; Libraries and institutions -- New York (State) -- New York -- Drawings.; Museum buildings -- New York (State) -- New York -- Designs and plans.; Museum buildings -- New York (State) -- New York -- Drawings.; Central Park West (New York, N.Y.) -- Buildings, structures, etc.; New York (N.Y.) -- History -- Societies, etc.; Greenberg, Allan; Skolnick, Lee; Beyer Blinder Belle, Architects & Planners; Bovis Lend Lease Consulting; New-York Historical Society -- Archives; New-York Historical Society -- Buildings
- Series I. General Subject Files, 1938-2017; 21.58 Linear feet in one document box, two flat boxes, and several drawers of oversize folders
  Scope and Contents Note
  The General Subject Files series includes records of various building projects dating from the 1940s and forward. The distinguishing feature of this series is that each project documented in it includes a relatively small number of records for each project. These projects range from small, highly focused work, such as the installation of railings at the front entrance in the mid-1970s, to large scale work such as the installation of air-conditioning in the mid-1960s.
  The content of the series appears to have been compiled from a variety of sources. Accordingly, the content is uneven and incomplete as to any particular project. Most documents lack fuller context including whether the work described was completed or not. Nonetheless, many documents provide important information about key projects. These include, among others, the Historic American Buildings Survey (HABS) Photographic Documentation taken in 2008 and 2010 in advance of interior and exterior renovation work done at that time, including in the auditorium; the early concept documents from Lee H. Skolnick for the DiMenna Children's Museum (2008-2010); and concept documents from Donna Lawrence Productions for the Orientation Theater (2008-2011).
  Arrangement Note
  The series is arranged in rough chronological order.
  - Water Main Break, 1938, 1948 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
    Includes photographs of water main and sidewalk excavation (1948). Includes two blueprints of gauges (1938).
  - Drawings for Glass Case, 1952 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
  - Proposed New Mezzanine Floor, East Gallery, 1951 June (Drawer 12A-B7, Folder 1)
    Includes one drawing on tissue paper with elevations, lighting plan, and various details. Drawn by architects R.B. O'Connor & W.H. Kilham, Jr.
  - 15 West 76th Street. Proposed Alterations, 1950s? (Drawer 12A-B7, Folder 2)
    Drawing by Garrett H. Winter (N-YHS Superintendent).
  - Air Conditioning Estimates, 1953, 1961, 1965 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
    Includes report and correspondence from consulting engineers Meyer, Strong & Jones (1960s). See also folder below: Third Floor Office Proposal [Air Conditioning] for related 1965 blueprint.
  - Insurance Map for N-YHS, 1955 February (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
    Includes a map drawn by Marsh & McLennan highlighting the N-YHS building and its property at 15 West 76th Street.
  - Floor Space Square Footage Calculations (1 of 2), 1956 September (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5)
    Includes room by room dimensions and square foot calculations taken by N-YHS Superintendent Garret H. Winter. A set of oversize schematic floor plans were separated to the following folder.
  - Floor Space Square Footage Calculations (2 of 2). Oversize, 1956? (Offsite-box 28, Folder 8)
    Includes oversize schematic of floor plans identifying the purpose of each space in the building. The document is undated but likely relevant in 1956 as it was included in folder with Winter's space calculations of that year.
  - Third Floor Office Proposal [Air Conditioning], 1965 May 20 (Drawer 12A-B7, Folder 3)
    Includes one blueprint of a plan for air conditioning on the 3rd floor by engineers Meyer, Strong and Jones (drawing #HV-4). The blueprint is annotated with proposed changes of office locations, possibly also from 1965.
  - Meyer, Strong & Jones, 1965-1966 (Drawer 9B-B5, Folder 4)
    Includes blueprints and some bluelines of plans of lighting layouts and air conditioning for the basement through the 4th floor.
  - Moore & Hutchins, Architects, 1965-1966 (Drawer 9B-B5, Folder 6)
    Includes blueline drawings, principally those drawn with the mechanical & electrical engineers Meyer, Strong & Jones for basement ductwork, piping and mechanical equipment spaces; ductwork ventilation plans for the 1st through 4th floors; and schedules and details. Also includes Moore & Hutchins's roof & skylight plan.
  - Moore & Hutchins, Architects, 1966 (Drawer 9B-B5, Folder 5)
    Includes blueline drawings, principally those drawn with the mechanical & electrical engineers Meyer, Strong & Jones for lighting in the Reading Room and 4th Floor and for gallery wireway. Also one plan drawn by Gotham Lighting Corporation and approved by Moore & Hutchins. Also includes a voided architectural and structural roof plan.
  - Moore & Hutchins, Architects, 1966 (Drawer 9B-B5, Folder 7)
    Includes blueline drawings drawn with the mechanical & electrical engineers Meyer, Strong & Jones for lighting in the basement, roof, and 4th floor; light and power riser diagram; and wiring schedules.
  - Robertshaw-Fulton Controls Company, 1961, 1966 (Drawer 9B-B5, Folder 8)
    Includes drawings of valve schedules (1961) and plans for heating controls, drawn for architects Moore and Hutchins and engineers Meyer, Strong & Jones (1966).
  - W-M Metal Works, 1966 (Drawer 9B-B5, Folder 3)
    Includes bluelines of plans of ductwork in basement and of fan room (#1-B, 3-B, 4-B, 5-B, 6-B, 7-B (final), 8-FRB, 9-FRB, 10-FRB, 11-FRB Architects: Moore & Hutchings. Engineer: Meyer, Strong & Jones.
  - Basement Ducts. Field Check, Undated (1960s?) (Drawer 12A-B7, Folder 4)
    Includes two blueline drawings by an unidentified drafter.
  - Landmarks Preservation Committee, 1966, 1973 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
    Includes a copy of the Commission's designation of the N-YHS building as a Landmark (1966) and an incomplete copy of the "Historic District Designation Report" for Central Park West, 76th Street (1973).
  - Landmarks Permit for Minor [Lighting] Work, 1973-1974 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 7)
  - Castro-Blanco Piscioneri and Feder, Architects, 1970, 1972 (Drawer 9B-B5, Folder 9)
    Includes bluelines of floor plans for the cellar through 4th floor (drawings #1-5). Drawn in 1970 with revisions in 1972.
  - Castro-Blanco Piscioneri and Feder, Architects, 1971 (Drawer 9B-B5, Folder 10)
    Includes photocopies and one blueline of floor plans for the cellar through roof (drawings #1-6). Drawn in July 1971 with one revision in September 1971.
  - Castro-Blanco Piscioneri and Feder, Architects, 1970, 1972 (Drawer 9B-B5, Folder 11)
    Includes two floor plans on Mylar: a 1st floor plan (1970) and a 4th floor plan (M-4, 1972), with consulting engineer Richard Hill.
  - Castro-Blanco Piscioneri and Feder, Architects, 1971, 1973 (Drawer 9B-B5, Folder 12)
    Includes bluelines of floor plans (#1 to 6), stamped as inspector's official copy. Plan #6 (roof) has the original 1971 plan and the revised 1973 plan, with related amendment application filed with the Department of Buildings.
  - Safety First Products Corp., 1973 (Drawer 12A-B8, Folder 1)
    Includes bluelines of plans for the fire protection system.
  - Certificate of Occupancy (#73963), 1973 November 12 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 8)
  - Front Steps Railing (1 of 2), 1974-1975 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 9)
    Includes proposals and drawings by P.A. Fiebiger, Inc. for iron railings for the main entrance stairs and vestibule stair. Includes approval and permit card from the Landmarks Preservation Commission. The two drawings by Fiebiger were moved to the following oversize drawer.
  - Front Steps Railing (2 of 2). Oversize, 1974-1975 (Drawer 12A-B7, Folder 5)
    Includes two whiteprints of drawings by P.A. Fiebiger, Inc. for proposed iron railings for main entrance stair and vestibule stair.
  - Meyer, Strong & Jones, 1974-1975 (Drawer 12A-B8, Folder 2)
    Includes plans and progress prints drawn by the mechanical & electrical engineers of riser diagrams, halon system, storage rooms, book stacks, wiring, and schedules. Also includes one plan drawn by Fire Controls Inc. related to halon release.
  - Fire Controls, Inc., 1975 (Drawer 12A-B8, Folder 3)
    Includes floor layouts, riser diagrams, and smoke detection system wiring diagram.
  - J & J Fire Safety Corp., 1975 (Drawer 12A-B8, Folder 4)
    Includes one blueline plan of control system with sequence of operation.
  - Morse & Harvey, Architects, 1980 November (Drawer 12A-B8, Folder 5)
    Includes two sheets of a blueline plan for a museum staff lounge.
  - Library Conservation Studio, Undated (1980s?) (Drawer 12A-B7, Folder 6)
    Includes two bluelines of plans, electrical and elevations, by an unidentified drafter.
  - [Exhibition Spaces in Corridors and Library?], 1983 (Drawer 12A-B8, Folder 6)
    Includes two untitled drawings by an unidentified drafter.
  - Charles E. Broudy & Associates, Architects, 1985 (Drawer 12A-B8, Folder 8)
    Includes bluelines of plans for the Museum Store, including 4 sheets issued for bid, a floor plan, and a rendering of the view from the door.
  - Welton Becket Associates, Architects & Engineers, 1986 (Drawer 12A-B8, Folder 9)
    Includes eight sheets of plans for the basement level Tiffany Center, including plans of location, demolition, construction, reflected ceiling, details, electrical, finishes, and furniture.
  - Welton Becket Associates, Architects & Engineers, 1986 (Drawer 12A-B8, Folder 10)
    Includes bluelines and photocopies of plans for a painting storage room. See also the storage room plans below in the folder attributed to Skidmore Owens.
  - [Skidmore Owings Merrill (SOM)?], 1988-1989 (Drawer 12A-B8, Folder 11)
    Includes drawings for storage rooms for objects, painting, and paper. See also the Welton Becket Associates folder above.
  - D.M.C. Hopping, 1987-1989 (Drawer 12A-B8, Folder 12)
    Includes blueline plans for the Luman Reed Gallery, including elevations of the gallery and doorways, details, floor plans, and windows.
  - Paintings Conservation Lab Construction Photographs, 1988-1989 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 10)
  - Schematic for Auditorium Audiovisual System, 1989 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 11)
  - Luman Reed Gallery. Door Panel Templates, [1989] (Drawer 12A-B8, Folder 13)
  - "Safety First" Poster, 1990s? (Drawer 12A-B8, Folder 14)
    Includes three construction site posters used by Clayton Wilson Construction, Inc. to post site-specific emergency information.
  - Objects Conservation Lab, 1993-1995 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 12)
  - Library Office & Reading Room Renovations, 2001-2002 (Drawer 12A-B8, Folder 15)
    Includes various documents related to the renovation, including a compact storage survey, plans for compact storage by architects Beyer Blinder Belle, and a schedule by Westerman Construction Company.
  - Reading Room Floor Plan, 2006 November (Offsite-box 1, Folder 13)
  - Comtec Comprehensive Fire Technologies. Fire Suppression System Training and Maintenance Manual for Print Room, [2006] (Offsite-box 1, Folder 14)
  - Platt Byard Dovell White, Architects. Architecture for the Strategic Plan, 2006 November 9 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 15)
    Includes hard-copy proposal and a CD.
  - Platt Byard Dovell White, Architects. Phase V Capital Program-Cellar Plan, 2007 March 2 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 16)
  - Platt Byard Dovell White, Architects. Proposed East Elevation, 2007 March 20 (Drawer 9B-B6, Folder 1)
    One mounted drawing of the front (Central Park West) of the building.
  - Floor Plans, 2007 June, September (Offsite-box 28, Folder 5)
    Includes plans of existing and proposed layouts by floor, by an unidentified drafter.
  - Miscellaneous Design Images and Plans, 2007-2008 (Offsite-box 28, Folder 3)
  - Richard Meier & Partners, Architects. Design Proposal, 2007 November 15 (Offsite-box 28, Folder 4)
  - Platt Byard Dovell White, Architects. Phase V, Stages1A, 1B, 2A, 2B: Construction Documents, 2008 April 1 (Offsite-box 28, Folder 1)
  - Platt Byard Dovell White, Architects. Logistic Plans & Schedule, 2008 May 21 (Offsite-box 28, Folder 2)
  - Lee H. Skolnick. Design Renderings, 2007 November 26 (Offsite-box 29, Folder 7)
  - Lee H. Skolnick. Design Renderings, 2008 January 8 (Offsite-box 29, Folder 6)
  - Lee H. Skolnick. Identification/Signage Kick-Off Meeting, 2008 July 17 (Offsite-box 29, Folder 5)
  - Lee H. Skolnick. Identity Study, 2009 July 2 (Drawer 9B-B6, Folder 2)
    Includes one mounted rendering of the front entrance (Option 1, Draft 1).
  - Lee H. Skolnick. DiMenna Children's Museum (4 folders), 2008 July-2010 August (Offsite-box 29, Folder 1-4)
    Includes renderings, concept designs (2009), schematic design (2009), and fabrication documents (2010).
  - Lee H. Skolnick. DiMenna Children's Museum., 2009? (Drawer 9B-B6, Folder 3)
    Includes one mounted "vision rendering" of the gallery.
  - Historic American Buildings Survey (HABS) Photographic Documentation, 2008-2009 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 17)
    Includes 17 interior and exterior photographs taken in connection with proposed renovations and in conformance with a Letter of Resolution among N-YHS, the Empire State Development Corporation, and the New York State Office of Parks, Recreation and Historic Preservation.
  - Donna Lawrence Productions. Orientation Theater Experience (5 folders), 2008-2011 (Offsite-box 29, Folder 8-12)
    Includes booklets on preliminary treatment (2008), final approved treatment with key storyboard frames (2009), revisions and new design and approved final (2010), preliminary script with key storyboards (2010), and revised script with key storyboard frames (2011).
  - Historic American Buildings Survey (HABS) Photographic Documentation. Auditorium (2 folders), 2010 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 18-19)
    Includes 3 sets of 9 photographs each.
  - Auditorium Plans by Platt Byard Dovell White, 2010 August (Drawer 12A-B7, Folder 19)
    Scope and Contents
    Package 2: Primary Scope. With architectural, structural and mechanical plans.
    Immediate Source of Acquisition
    Transfered to Archives, 2020.
  - Reading Room Renovation, 2011 (Drawer 12A-B8, Folder 16)
    Includes two proposals with drawings of plans for bookcases, cabinets, and display cases, by Craz Woodworking Associates, Inc. and by Bunny Williams, Inc. (Architect G.P. Schafer).
  - 4th Floor Glass [Tiffany] Gallery & Education Media Center, 2012 February (Offsite-box 29, Folder 13)
    Booklet for Capital Projects, Fiscal Years 2013 & 2014, specifically plans and images covering the 4th floor gallery (by Eva Jiricna, architects) and the education media center (Platt Byard Dovell White, architects).
  - Poulin + Morris Designs for 4th Floor, 2017 January (Offsite-box 29, Folder 14)
    4 sheets: East Corridor/Roy J. Zuckerberg Hall of American Silver (elevation, plan view); East Corridor/Women's History Center (elevation, plan view); John L. & Sue Ann Weinberg Mezzanine (elevation, plan view); and Norman S. Benzaquen Grand Staircase (elevation, plan view).
- Series II. 1990s Capital Improvement Projects, circa 1984-2001 (bulk 1989-2000); 16.38 Linear feet in 26 document boxes and two drawers of oversize folders
  The series includes records related to the major building renovation initiatives N-YHS pursued in the 1990s. These included both infrastructure upgrades, such as to the HVAC system and roofing, and to gallery space, notably the Henry Luce III Center for the Study of American Culture (Luce Center), an open storage facility on the 4th floor that opened in 2000. The series includes files of Chief Operating Officer Ed Norris as they related to the three phase construction project that ran from 1994 to 2000. The series also includes earlier planning and project documents beginning in 1989, some of which were accomplished, such as the renovation and re-installation of the Luman Reed Gallery, and others that could not be fully pursued until later in the decade. These earlier files appear to have been compiled at some point from various departments and offices, likely including from President and Chief Executive Officer Barbara Debs (BKD) and from Museum Director Holly Hotchner (HH).
  The series includes studies and assessments, contracts, status reports, meeting notes, correspondence with architects and with principal contractors, payment requisitions and supporting documentation, permits, budgets, schedules, and other documents concerning the planning and implementation of the renovation projects. The series includes many architectural drawings, principally those from 1989-1990 from the firm of Allan Greenberg, Architect (AGA). The series has a few architectural plans related to the the more extensive project work conducted in the second half of the 1990s.
  The series is organized in three subseries:
  Subseries II.A. Initial Planning & Projects
  Subseries II.B. Construction Phases I-III
  Subseries II.C. Architectural Plans
  - Subseries II.A. Initial Planning & Projects, circa 1984-1994 (bulk, 1989-1993); 5.02 Linear feet
    The Initial Planning & Projects subseries includes documents primarily related to the range of projects targeted for work beginning in 1989, but for various reasons, principally financial, were not all completed. The series centers on the work from 1989-1990 of the architectural firm Allan Greenberg, Architect (AGA), and their specialized consultants including H.B. Fishman (roof repairs); Facade Maintenance Design (façade conservation); Ambrosino, DePinto and Schmieder (heating, ventilation, and air conditioning (HVAC), and electrical); Ambient Labs (asbestos remediation); Severud Associates (structural engineering); George Sexton (lighting); and Clayton-Wilson (construction manager). Among the specific areas impacted by these renovations were the Luman Reed Gallery and the Print Room. Some of the contracted work extended to assessments of the townhouse owned by N-YHS at 15 West 76th Street. Additional projects, including those designed by architect Richard Jansen in the early-mid 1990s are also documented.
    The source of the documents is uncertain, but appear to have been compiled at some point from various departments and offices, likely including from President and Chief Executive Officer Barbara Debs (BKD) and from Museum Director Holly Hotchner (HH). Documents include assessments, condition reports, images, correspondence, proposals, budgets and estimates, landmark alteration applications, permits, and contracts. The subseries includes some architectural plans, but see subseries II.C for the bulk of the drawings by Allan Greenberg, Architect.